All right בוקר טוב *boker tov* everybody. Today's we will we are
דף daf *daf* behind so today's דף *daf* is דף ז *daf
zayin* and even for that we start on ו עמוד ב *vav
amud bet* at the bottom, and it is the two dots about
20 lines before the end of the דף *daf*, five words in,
ואמר ve'amar, רבי חלבו Rabbi Helbo. *v'amar Rabbi Chelbo*. So ואמר רבי
חלבו אמר רב הונא ve-amar Rebbi Chelbo amar Rav Huna *v'amar Rabbi
Chelbo amar Rav Huna*. So now we're having a number of statements
here of רב הונא Rav Huna. *Rav Huna*, רבי חלבו Rabbi Helbo
*Rabbi Chelbo* in the name of רב הונא *Rav Huna*. So אמר
רבי חלבו אמר רב הונא Amar Rabbi Helbo amar Rav Huna. לעולם
יהא אדם זהיר בתפילת המנחה *amar Rabbi Chelbo amar Rav Huna l'olam
yei adam zahir b'tefillat hamencha*. You should always be careful about מנחה
*Mincha*, שהרי אליהו לא נענה אלא Ela, בתפילת המנחה *sheharei Eliyahu lo
ne'eneh ela b'tefillat hamincha*. אליהו *Eliyahu* was only answered by God at
the מנחה *Mincha* time. שנאמר Shene'emar *she'ne'emar*, this was when he was
having the war with the prophets of the בעל *Baal*, שנאמר shene'emar,
*she'ne'emar* as it says, ויהי בעלות המנחה ויגש אליהו הנביא *v'yehi ba'alot
hamincha vayigash Eliyahu hanavi*. It was when the at the rise at
the time the מנחה *Mincha* of מנחה *Mincha* אליהו הנביא *Eliyahu hanavi*
came forth. ויאמר *vayomer* he said, ענני ה' ענני *aneni Hashem aneni*,
answer me God answer me. And what is the double language of
answer me? ענני שתרד אש מן השמים *aneni shetered esh min hashamayim*,
first of all that my that the sacrifice there should be a
miracle that shows the sacrifice is accepted, fire should come out from
heaven. וענני *v'aneni* answer me שלא יאמרו מעשה כשפים הם *shelo yomru
ma'aseh kshafim hem*. Even after it's a miracle, people have ways of
discounting what they see. So don't let them say that it's just
witchcraft. So anyway you see that that was when he was answered
at the מנחה *Mincha* time. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan. אומר *Rabbi Yochanan
omer*, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan *Rabbi Yochanan* says, אף תפילת ערבית *af
tefillat arvit*.
Not only מנחה *Mincha*, what about מעריב *Maariv*? שנאמר shene'emar, תכון תפלתי
קטרת לפניך משאת כפי מנחת ערב *she'ne'emar tikan tefillati ketoret lefanecha mas'at
kapai minchat arev*. Let my prayer be accepted like the incense in
front of you, the offering of my hands like the gift of
evening. So it's ערב *arev*, at the evening, מנחה *Mincha* here not
meaning the מנחה *Mincha* time but meaning the meaning a gift. רב
נחמן בר יצחק אמר amar, *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar*, what do
you mean? אף תפילת שחרית *af tefillat shacharit*. Let's not forget about
שחרית *Shacharit*. שנאמר shene'emar, ה' בקר תשמע קולי בקר אערך לך ואצפה
*she'ne'emar Hashem boker tishma koli boker e'erach lach va'atzapeh*. God in the
morning hear my voice, in the morning I will sort of order
my prayer out for you and look and I will look towards
you. So of course, you know, you understand why the second moves
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that you don't want to make מנחה
*Mincha* somehow give it more emphasis than the others, but you do
sort of wonder once you say everything is important whether you've really
made what the point of the whole thing is. You do understand
I believe the importance of מנחה *Mincha* in the sense that on
the one hand מעריב *Maariv* is a little second-class status because there's
a discussion whether מעריב *Maariv* is רשות *reshut* or חובה *chova*, and
also people tend to be pretty tired at night and maybe not
give it the focus that they need. So you understand why you
want to underscore the importance of מעריב *Maariv*. But מנחה *Mincha* in
particular is like right in the middle of the day. And there's
not a power to doing something first thing in the morning, last
thing at night. You're looking forward to the day or you're reflecting
on the past day. מנחה
*Mincha* right in the middle of all the busyness of the day
to stop and to דאוון *daven* and so on, you understand why
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort of wants to underscore the importance of
trying to be careful about תפילת מנחה *tefillat Mincha*. But again after
then you say oh how about מעריב *Maariv*? How about שחרית *Shacharit*?
Even if it ended at מעריב *Maariv*, I understand that מעריב *Maariv*
is one that also needs a little חיזוק *chizuk*. But anyway by
the end of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* it's not so clear to
me what we've accomplished. Anyway, now the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* continues. ואמר
רבי Rebbe חלבו אמר רב הונא *v'amar Rabbi Chelbo amar Rav Huna*,
another statement in the name of רבי Rebbe, חלבו *Rabbi Chelbo* in
the name of רב הונא *Rav Huna*. כל הנהנה מסעודת חתן ואינו
משמחו *kol hane'eneh misudat chatan v'eino mesamcho*. So now we're moving away
from תפילה *tefilla*. Anybody who benefits from the wedding feast of the
חתן *chatan*, note it just says חתן *chatan* interestingly, and does not
rejoice him. Again the him, the focus on the חתן *chatan*. עובר
בחמישה קולות *over b'chamisha kolot*, transgresses the five voices. שנאמר shene'emar, קול
ששון וקול שמחה kol sason vekol simcha. קול חתן וקול כלה קול
אומרים הודו ה' צבאות *she'ne'emar kol sasson v'kol simcha kol chatan v'kol
kalla kol omrim hodu Hashem Tzevaot*. So all of the voices of
the rejoicing of the חתן *chatan* and the כלה *kalla* and the
praising of God have arrived. Okay.
All of these voices you will have sort of transgressed in the
sense that this is what's supposed to be being created at the
wedding feast. It's a feast yes, but it's a feast of giving
joy to the חתן *chatan* and כלה *kalla*, praising God, and you're
not doing that. You're just making it about your own serving your
own appetite and desires. And so therefore you have transgressed all of
these voices as it were the value of what you're really supposed
to be accomplishing here. ואם משמחו *v'im mesamcho*, it's sort of like
the opposite of what רב ישראל Yisrael. סלנטר *Rav Yisrael Salanter* used
to say. You know רב ישראל Yisrael, סלנטר *Rav Yisrael Salanter* said
יענעמס גשמיות איז דיין רוחניות *yenems gashmius is dayn ruchnius*. Another person's
physical needs are your spiritual needs. Well here what you're taking is
something that's supposed to be a spiritual experience and you're turning it
into just a satisfying of your physical needs. ואם משמחו *v'im mesamcho*,
but if you do make him rejoice, מה שכרו *ma secharo*, what
how will you be rewarded? So אמר רבי Rebbe יהושע בן לוי
זוכה לתורה שניתנה בחמישה קולות *amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi zocheh l'Torah
shenitna b'chamisha kolot*. You will merit תורה Torah *Torah* that is given
in five voices. שנאמר shene'emar, ויהי ביום השלישי בהיות הבקר ויהי קלת
וברקים וענן כבד על ההר וקל שפר *she'ne'emar v'yehi bayom hashlishi biheyot
haboker v'yehi kolot u'vrakim v'anan kaved al hahar v'kol shofar* etc. ויהי
קול השופר הולך וחזק מאד *v'yehi kol hashofar holech v'chazek m'od*. Anyway
there are five voices there corresponding to the five voices of making
the חתן *chatan* and the כלה *kalla* rejoice. And maybe here exactly
is that point as well which is that although this is more
sort of it's a מצוה *mitzvah* and it's the rejoicing of the
חתן *chatan* and כלה *kalla* but ultimately Exactly, you know, it should
also be connected to what we might often consider to be a
higher form of speech, the speech of תורה. Torah, And ultimately, when
somebody is making somebody joyous at their wedding, you know, that is,
you know, that type of sort of גמילות חסדים gemilut chasadim essentially
ultimately allows you to merit תורה Torah as well.
Is that really true? והכתיב וכל העם רואים את הקולות. Vehaktiv vechol
ha'am ro'im et hakolot. So that makes six, not five. So it
says אותן קולות דקודם מתן תורה. otan kolot dekodem matan Torah. Oh,
that was before מתן תורה. matan Torah. At מתן תורה matan Torah
there was only five. All right. רב פפא אמר כאילו הקריב תודה.
Rav Papa amar ke'ilu hikriv todah. It is not not just that
you merit or not that you merit five voices of תורה, torah
rather it is like you offered up a sacrifice of thanksgiving. שנאמר
מביאים תודה בית ה׳. Shene'emar mevi'im todah beit Hashem. They bring the
תודה todah in the house of God, that is at the end
of קול ששון וקול שמחה. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר כאילו בנה
אחת מחורבות ירושלים. Rabbi Nachman bar Yitzchak amar ke'ilu bana achat michurvot
Yerushalayim.
It's like you built one of the destroyed places of Jerusalem, remember
echoing back or I don't know the גמרות Gemaras we had a
few days ago about the חורבות ירושלים. churvot Yerushalayim. שנאמר כי אשיב
את שבות הארץ כבראשונה אמר ה׳. Shene'emar ki ashiv et shevut ha'aretz
kevarishonah amar Hashem. At the end because I will also
at the end of that verse I will return the land as
it had been originally. Now of course you understand here the significance
of these last two. Certainly of the תודה, todah, thanksgiving, you know
is that when we connect with other people's joy, you know normally
we talk about thanksgiving when it occurs to us, but you know
if we feel that communal sense then we have that sense of
gratitude and thanksgiving when it connects to others and being משמח חתן
וכלה mesameach chatan vekallah is connecting at that communal level. Also, you
know if you can be happy about other people's things it's because
you can also it's also an expression of your appreciation and gratitude
for what you've been blessed with as well. The אחת מחורבות ירושלים
achat michurvot Yerushalayim is the most obvious because you know the whole
idea about you know the נבואה nevuah in ירמיהו Yirmiyahu and the
ברכה bracha one of the שבע ברכות sheva brachot right is that
you know seeing into the future when once again Jerusalem will be
built up and there will be קול חתן וקול ששון וקול
שמחה kol chatan vekol sason vekol simcha in the רחובות ירושלים rechovot
Yerushalayim as opposed to the חורבות ירושלים. churvot Yerushalayim. So by creating,
you know, sustaining this experience and this joy it ultimately is helping
to bring about that time when that will be once again experienced
in you know a rebuilt Israel, which is you know which is
the נבואה nevuah of ירמיהו, Yirmiyahu, the אחת מחורבות ירושלים. achat michurvot
Yerushalayim. Which by the way makes it of course so powerful nowadays
when these things are a reality and when you participate in a
wedding in ירושלים Yerushalayim and you're seeing these פסוקים pesukim which are
about ירמיהו Yirmiyahu sort of, you know, envisioning only in messianic times
will this experience be had again. So that obviously is the significance
of those of those דרשות. drashot. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara
continues. We're still not done with רבי Rebbe חלבו. אמר רבי Rebbe's
חלבו אמר רב הונא. So said רבי Rebbe חלבו in the name
of רב הונא. כל אדם שיש בו יראת שמים דבריו נשמעים. Kol
adam sheyesh bo yirat shamayim devarav nishma'im. Anybody that has awe of
heaven, you know as a pious individual we should say, his words
are heard. Which tends to be you know not just a sort
of a ברכה bracha metaphysical, it's true, you know, certain people that
they really exude piety, you know, you really pay attention to what
they're saying. שנאמר shene'emar, as the verse says not always like the
charismatic people, sometimes, you know, sometimes and very often it is the
charismatic people but sometimes it's also the humble pious people that you
really, you know, that really get, you know, you pay you hear
what they have to say. As it says סוף דבר הכל נשמע
את האלהים ירא, sof davar hakol nishma et ha-Elokim yera, the end
of the matter everything is heard,
God you should fear. So of course פשט pshat of the פסוקים
pasukim is bottom line fear God. But here we're interpreting it to
mean when is הכל נשמע hakol nishma when אלהים ירא Elokim yera
when it's a person who fears God. מאי כי זה כל האדם?
Mai ki zeh kol ha'adam? What's meant by the end of the
verse this is all human for all humans? אמר רבי אלעזר אמר
הקדוש ברוך הוא כל העולם כולו לא נברא אלא בשביל זה. Amar
Rabbi Elazar amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu kol ha'olam kulo lo nivra ela
bishvil zeh. This is כל האדם. kol ha'adam. This person has יראת
אלהים, yirat Elokim, awe of God. This is why everybody was created
to achieve this to be a ירא אלהים. yarei Elokim. Now it's
not necessarily just that, you know, everybody should be this. This is
the model but it seems to be saying something more that, you
know, that maybe you need to have a million people for one
true ירא אלהים yarei Elokim to come out. Or maybe another way
of saying which you'll see maybe in the next דרשות drashot is,
you know, for one person to survive to to make, you know,
to make a way of it in the world you need a
lot of people right? For the clothes you're wearing you need somebody
to have raised the sheep, sheared the sheep, made them into, you
know, wool, woven the cloth. For the food on your table I
mean there's, you know, millions of different people or thousands of different
people that go into, you know, just the things we benefit from
every single day. So everybody in the world exists in order that
this one righteous person should be able to exist. Let's that's that's
another way of reading it which let's see seems to be the
next line. Let's keep on reading. רבי אבא בר כהנא אמר שקול
זה כנגד כל העולם כולו. Rabbi Abba bar Kahana amar shakol zeh
keneged kol ha'olam kulo. That's a different statement. He's equivalent to the
whole entire world. A ירא אלהים yarei Elokim is worth everybody. רבי
שמעון בן עזאי אומר ואמרי לה רבי שמעון בן זומא אומר כל
העולם כולו לא נברא אלא לצוות לזה. Rabbi Shimon ben Azzai omer
ve'amrei leh Rabbi Shimon ben Zoma omer kol ha'olam kulo lo nivra
ela letzavot lazeh. The whole rest of the world. The whole rest
of the world was created just to accompany this person. You know,
you can't live outside of society. So okay, he needs friends, he
needs a he needs a community. So that's why everybody else is
around, but the real person that matters is this one person. So
on the one hand, you know, it's a beautiful statement about how
important it is to achieve יראת אלוהים yirat elohim and how it's
something we should all be striving for. On the other hand, you
know, it is quite hierarchical about the value of everybody else. And
it's interesting that רמב"ם Rambam in I think מורה נבוכים, Moreh Nevuchim,
I'm trying to remember, but it might be one of his other
writings, might be somewhere in in his פירוש המשנה, Peirush HaMishnah, you
know, uses this but reframes it in terms of the philosopher, that
the only people that really matter are the philosophers and the people
that really have pure intellectual understanding of God. So why does everybody
else exist? Well, everybody else exists because you can't have the philosophers
without everybody else. You need somebody to be planting the crops and
somebody to be raising the sheep, and you need the rest of
the world in order so that you can have the philosophers. So
anyway, it does create an interesting way of thinking about the structure
of society at the same time while praising what the accomplishments of
this person are.
Okay, is everybody there? Is everybody online, everybody hearing me?
Hello? Okay, fine. All right, so we continue.
Yep. Okay. ואמר רבי חלבו אמר רב הונא כל שיודע
בחברו שהוא רגיל ליתן
לו שלום, kol she-yodeia
be-chavero she-hu ragil litein
lo shalom,
anybody that knows his friend you know when he greets is is
often greets you you know when you see him you know on
the street he'll say hello, how are you doing? So יקדים לו
שלום, yaktim lo shalom,
you should make a point of trying to beat him to it,
meaning don't wait, not like the context but you know if you
you know don't wait for him to express his you know enthusiasm
for seeing you and say שלום עליכם, shalom aleichem, it shouldn't be
only a one-way street, you should also try sometime to be the
person to initiate. You see him, you be excited, you say שלום
עליכם. shalom aleichem. שנאמר בקשו שלום ורדפהו, she-ne'emar bakeshu shalom ve-radfeihu,
to desire peace and to run after it. And although again here
it's translating peace in a narrow way like שלום עליכם, shalom aleichem,
how are you doing, you know obviously there's a power to that
that when you express that you you make people feel wanted and
and noticed and you know and and so and it's really important
that it goes in both directions. ואם נתן לו ולא החזיר, ve-im
natan lo ve-lo hechezir, and let's say you gave hello say hello
to somebody and he didn't respond hello back, so נקרא גזלן, nikra
gazlan, he's a
thief. שנאמר ואתם בערתם הכרם, she-ne'emar ve-atem bi-artem ha-kerem, you have destroyed
the
the the vineyard, גזלת העני בבתיכם, gezelat he-ani be-vateichem, the the theft
from the poor person is in your house. What do you steal
from the poor person? What you steal from the poor person isn't
his money, but it's other things. It's the fact that you know
that that that you know you were owed a hello and you
didn't get a hello, you stole the hello, you stole the שלום
עליכם shalom aleichem from this person. All he needed was your שלום
עליכם shalom aleichem to feel important, to feel welcome, and you didn't
give it to him. Now that by the way,
you know, I got to tell you just a little aside, it
really annoys the heck out of me on you know when you're
walking on the street and particularly on שבת, Shabbos, you know and
you see other people around and you say hello, שלום עליכם, shalom
aleichem, גוט שבת, Gut Shabbos, and they don't say anything back to
you. Like, oh, I don't know you, I don't have to say
anything back to you. You know, it feels to me that this
is like one of these places where it costs like nothing to
try to create a sense of connection and community and so on,
and some people still begrudge you the שלום עליכם. shalom aleichem. So
this גמרא Gemara I think is very much to the point in
terms of that.
Okay, so now moving on top of ז' עמוד א'. zayin amud
aleph. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי Amar Rebbi Yochanan mishum Rebbi
Yosi מניין שהקדוש ברוך הוא מתפלל. minayin she-HaKadosh Baruch Hu mitpallel. We
learned yesterday that God wore תפילין. tefillin. Now we're going to find
out that God also דאווענס. davens. שנאמר והביאותים אל הר קדשי ושמחתים
בבית תפלתי. she-ne'emar va-haviotim el har kodshi ve-simachtim be-veit tefillati. I will
bring them to my holy mountain and I will make them rejoice
in my house of prayer. תפלתם נאמר, tefillatam ne'emar, not, not the
house of their prayer, אלא תפלתי, ella tefillati, that my prayer, not
the prayer that I receive but presumably the prayer that I offer.
מכאן שהקדוש ברוך הוא מתפלל, mi-kan she-HaKadosh Baruch Hu mitpallel, here God
prays. Now while before when we had God wearing תפילין, tefillin, he
wore תפילין tefillin that spoke about the chosenness of Israel, it's going
to be interesting to see who God prays to since God will
not be praying to Israel. So let's see who God is praying
to. So מאי מצלי, mai matzlei, what does he pray? So אמר
רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב amar Rav Zutra bar Tuvia amar
Rav יהי רצון מלפני, yehi ratzon milfanai, here's what he prays. יהי
רצון מלפני, yehi ratzon milfanai, may it be the will in front
of me, may it be my will, שיכבשו רחמי את כעסי, she-yichbeshu
rachamay et ka'asi, that my compassion should overwhelm my anger, ויגולו רחמי
על מדותי, ve-yigolu rachamay al middotai, and the it's a beautiful verb
here ויגולו, ve-yigolu, my my compassion will like will wave over, the
waves of my compassion will will overcome my my other attributes, ואתנהג
עם בני
במדת הרחמים, ve-et-naheig im banai be-middat ha-rachamim, and I will deal with
my children with the with the attribute of compassion, ואכנס להם לפנים
משורת הדין, ve-ekaneis lahem lifnim mi-shurat ha-din, and I'll deal and I'll
bring enter in with them inside the letter of the law. and
I'll deal with them more than is deserving, you know, I'll be,
I'll give them the benefit of the doubt and I'll deal with
them more than is deserving. So it sounds funny that God is
praying to Himself, but I think any parent can really identify with
this prayer, that sometimes you have to say, oh, I just hope
I have the ability to show the compassion and not to get
angry at them. So, and that is sort of how we are
sort of imagining that God is praying as it were to himself
or trying to, you know, to bring forth that attribute. There's something
very beautiful, I mean obviously it's highly anthropomorphic and in that way
disturbing for those of us that really are troubled with anthropomorphism. But
on the other hand, there's something very beautiful about that struggle, about
the different ways in which you can deal with your children, deal
with other people. There's a place for מידת הדין midat hadin as
well. It's not that there's one that's bad and that's one that's
good. But, you know, the real hope that you're able to bring
forth, you know, the מידת הרחמים midat harachamim over the מידת הדין.
midat hadin.
So,
תניא, tanya, so the גמרא Gemara continues, אמר רבי ישמעאל בן אלישע,
amar rabbi yishmael ben elisha, so Rabbi Ishmael ben Elisha said, פעם
אחת, pa'am achat, now this is fascinating because here we have פעם
אחת נכנסתי להקטיר קטורת לפני ולפנים. pa'am achat nichnasti lehaktir ketoret lifnai
velifnim. So this Rabbi Ishmael ben Elisha is apparently a כהן גדול.
kohen gadol. And here he is, he's a speaker in a ברייתא.
braita. So first of all, it has to be a very early
ברייתא, braita, you know, written before the חורבן בית המקדש, churban beit
hamikdash, but also to have somebody who is a כהן גדול kohen
gadol also as a תנא tana in a ברייתא braita is pretty
interesting, unless it's just somebody is quoting him. You know, he's not
sort of there as a rabbi making this statement, but this is
a report of what he said. Anyway, he is also רבי ישמעאל
בן אלישע, rabbi yishmael ben elisha, so said רבי ישמעאל בן אלישע,
rabbi yishmael ben elisha, פעם אחת נכנסתי להקטיר קטורת לפני ולפנים, pa'am
achat nichnasti lehaktir ketoret lifnai velifnim, once I entered in the, you
know, the קודש קודשים kodesh kodashim to offer the, to offer incense.
וראיתי אכתריאל, vera'iti akatriel, I saw אכתריאל, akatriel, which literally means the
א alef is אב, ab, אכתריאל, akatriel, כתריאל katriel by son's name
is, which is not a name of an angel in anywhere of
תנ"ך, Tanakh, it's one place אכתריאל akatriel appears is in this גמרא,
Gemara one of the, one of the few places. Anyway, that the,
it means my crown is God, so יה ה' צבאות. ya hashem
tzevaot. So there you have this same אכתריאל akatriel but then being
identified with God, יה ה' צבאות ya hashem tzevaot is God, I
saw God שהוא יושב על כיסא רם ונישא, shehu yoshev al kise
ram venisa, was sitting there on a throne high and elevated. By
the way, that connects to the first אכתריאל, akatriel, like the crown,
wearing his crown, you know, sitting on his kingly throne, I saw
God. ואמר, and God said to me, there I was in the
קודש קודשים, kodesh kodashim, ישמעאל בני ברכני, yishmael beni barcheni, Ishmael my
son, give me a blessing. So here not just is God praying,
He's asking for a ברכה bracha from us. I mean, we sort
of say a ברכה bracha to God every day ברוך אתה ה',
baruch ata hashem, but we're more declaring that God is blessed. Here
God is asking us, you know, to sort of give him a
blessing, that He wants, He wants to be blessed by us. So,
you know, bless me. אמרתי לו, amarti lo, I said to Him,
יהי רצון מלפניך שיכבשו רחמיך את כעסך, yehi ratzon milfanecha sheyichbeshu rachamecha
et kasecha, may it be the will in front of You that
Your compassion will subjugate Your anger, ויגולו רחמיך על מידותיך, veyagolu rachamecha
al midotecha, Your compassion will wave, the wave will wash over Your,
Your other attributes, ותנהג עם בניך במידת הרחמים ותיכנס להם לפנים משורת
הדין, vetinhag im banecha bemidat harachamim vetikanes lahem lifnim mishurat hadin, just
like we said before. ונענע לי בראשו, venana li berosho, he nodded
with his head and he said like to show that he acquiesced
and presumably from there that's
how we know that that's what God prays because it shows that
that's exactly the prayer that he, the blessing that he wanted.
וקמשמע לן, vekamashma lan, it teaches
us שלא תהא ברכת הדיוט קלה בעיניך, shelo tehe birkat hedyot kala
be'einecha, God wants a blessing from even a person. So if God
wants a blessing from human beings, even if you receive a blessing
even from a, you know, from an insignificant person, that should be
important. Every blessing has significance and should have, should be of value.
So just two brief comments about this, one is the fact that
it uses the phrase כתר, keter, obviously it's here the image of
God on the throne, but also talks about God sort of, you
know, praying that his attribute, you have sort of this almost sense
if you were to do it in Freudian terms, you know, it's
sort of like the ego and it's grappling between the id and
the superego and so on. In kabbalistic terms, right, it's, you know,
God has these different attributes, they're the different ספירות. sefirot. And above
all the ספירות sefirot is like אין סוף, ein sof, the infinite
God that cannot be anthropomorphized. But sort of the first part that's
the top of the ספירות sefirot that can be anthropomorphized is כתר,
keter, is the crown. So the מהרש"א Maharsha tries to sort of
read that into this גמרא Gemara, and he says that's what's going
on, that the, the sort of, you know, the,
the expression of God that's כתר, keter, right, is here what's being
sort of embodied or expressed and the idea is that that should
have sort of influence over the other attributes, the other ספירות. sefirot.
So that's how he reads it and that does seem to fit
very nicely with this sense of like sort of, you know, if
we were to personify, the essence trying to deal with, grapple with,
pray, you know, in terms of the other attributes. So that's in
terms of sort of the basic part of the text. And the
last thing I just have to tell you about אל תהי ברכת
הדיוט קלה בעיניך. al tehi birkat hedyot kala be'einecha.
you know, so there's a story, well, there's two stories about being
asked for ברכות. Brachos. I'll tell you, I'll tell you one of
them. I mean, there's more, but anyway, one is somebody goes to
a רבי and says, you know, רבי, רבי give me a ברכה.
Bracha. So the רבי like ignores him, says don't bother me, whatever.
So the רבי's like, you know, assistant says says like, you know,
why are you doing that? Like, you know, the גמרא Gemara says
לא תהי ברכת הדיוט קלה בעיניך. Lo Tei Birkas Hedyos Kala Be-eynecha.
So he says, fine, you give him the ברכה. Bracha.
That was a joke. Anyway.
All right. So, anyway, the other version is, which you might have
heard, was somebody goes to Rav Soloveitchik and says, רבי give me
a ברכה, Bracha, to which he says, what, are you an apple?
So, anyway.
Those are two attitudes that I would say are not exactly fulfilling
the message of this
גמרא Gemara, of לא תהי ברכת קלה הדיוט בעיניך. Lo Tei Birkas
Kala Hedyos Be-eynecha. Anyway. Moving on.
Next discussion. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי מנין שאין מרצין לו
לאדם בשעת כעסו. Amar Rabbi Yochanan Mishum Rabbi Yosi Minayin She-ein Martzin
Lo Le-adam Bi-sh'as Ka'aso. So now we are, we've, I don't know,
I'm a little bit losing the thread here. It seems to be
that we're going back, we've had other sayings of רבי יוחנן. Not
sure if we've had any of רבי יוחנן משום mishum רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yosi, but certainly it is not exactly fitting into the theme.
But anyway, how do you know that you do not try to
appease somebody when they are angry? דכתיב פני ילכו והנחתי לך. De-chtiv
Panai Yaleichu Ve-hanichoti Lach. That my, so literally it means my face
will go in front of you and I will give rest to
you. So meaning when משה Moshe asks אם אין פניך הולכים, Im
Ein Panecha Holchim, right when God said he's going to remove the
שכינה Shechinah and God in the end says right after the חטא
העגל Cheit Ha-eigel that I will lead you, I won't be maybe
in your midst but I'll lead you. Anyway, here we're reading פני
Panai means like פנים של זעם, Panim Shel Za'am, like face of
anger, often פנים Panim is used in a context of anger. Let
my anger pass away, then I'll be calm with you, then I'll
deal with you. אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה המתן לי עד
שיעברו פנים של זעם ואניח לך. Amar Lo Ha-kadosh Baruch Hu Le-moshe
Hamtein Li Ad She-ya'avru Panim Shel Za'am Ve-anich Lach. Wait till my
face of anger passes by and then I will be, I will
give rest to you, then we can talk. Okay, which is obviously
very good advice. Sometimes you gotta wait for people to calm down
before you can talk to them. So now the גמרא Gemara says
ומי איכא רתחא קמי קודשא בריך הוא? U-mi Ika Ris'cha Kamei Kudsha
Brich Hu? Does God get angry? אין. In. Yes. דתניא, De-tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, pretty funny to ask that question since
a moment ago we said יכבשו רחמי את כעסי, Yichbeshu Rachamai Es
Ka'asi, right, let my רחמים Rachamim overrule my כעס, Ka'as, and now
we're saying does God get angry? Anyway, also pretty funny that anybody
that reads the תורה torah certainly sees God getting angry all the
time, so I don't exactly understand what the question is, but let's
see where the answer goes.
דתניא, De-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraita, ואל זועם בכל יום,
Ve-eil Zo'eim Be-chol Yom, God gets angry every day. וכמה זעמו? Ve-kamah
Za'amo? asks the גמרא, gemara רגע. Rega. How long is his anger,
his fiery anger? A רגע. Rega. וכמה רגע? Ve-chamah Rega? How long
is a רגע? Rega? אחד מחמשת ריבוא ושמונת אלפים ושמונה מאות ושמונים
ושמונה בשעה. Echad Mi-chameshet Rivo U-shmonat Alafim U-shmoneh Me'ot U-shmonim Ve-shmoneh Be-sha'ah.
One part out of
fifty-eight thousand eight hundred and
eighty-eight of an hour. I have no idea where they got that
number. Somebody can figure that out. Somebody can also figure out what
percentage of a second that is, but anyway, it's pretty infinitesimal. Okay,
וזו היא רגע, Ve-zo Hi Rega, that's a, that is the רגע,
Rega, a רגע. Rega. ואין כל בריה יכולה לכוין אותה שעה, Ve-ein
Kol Beriyah Yecholah Le-chavein Osah Sha'ah, and nobody could could sort of
pinpoint that that moment that, you know, it's a portion of a
second, חוץ מבלעם הרשע. Chutz Mi-bil'am Ha-rasha. בלעם Bil'am had the ability
to identify that one millionth of a second or whatever thousandth of
a second that God got angry.
דכתיב ביה ויודע דעת עליון, De-chtiv Bei Ve-yodei'a Da'at Elyon, right בלעם
Bil'am says about himself, I know the knowledge of God, I know
what God knows. So the גמרא gemara says, it's gotta be one
of the best sort of like punchlines of the גמרא, gemara you
know, deflating lines, השתא דעת בהמתו לא הוה ידע דעת עליון הוה
ידע? Hashta Da'at Behemto Lo Hava Yadai Da'at Elyon Hava Yadai? He
didn't know what his animal was thinking, he didn't know what his
donkey was thinking, he knows what God is thinking? אלא, but rather
מלמד שהיה יודע לכוין. Melamed She-hayah Yodei'a Le-chavein. He didn't know what
God was thinking, what he knew was one like trick, שהיה יודע
לכוין אותה שעה שהקדוש ברוך הוא כועס בה. She-hayah Yodei'a Le-chavein Osah
Sha'ah She-ha-kadosh Baruch Hu Ko'eis Bah. He knew how to pinpoint that
one moment that God got angry. והיינו דאמר להו נביא לישראל, Ve-haynu
De-amar Lehu Navi Le-yisrael, and we're going to see in a minute
that if you could, he could have sort of tapped into that
anger of God he could have exploited it and that was his
hope in order to curse ישראל. Yisrael, והיינו דאמר נביא לישראל, Ve-haynu
De-amar Navi Le-yisrael, and that's what the נביא Navi says to ישראל,
עמי זכור נא מה יעץ בלק מלך מואב, Ammi Zechor Na Mah
Ya'atz Balak Melech Mo'av, remember what בלק Balak tried to do to
you, ומה ענה אותו בלעם, U-mah Anah Oso Bil'am, and in the
end
it says למען דעת צדקות ה, Lema'an Da'at Tzidkot Hashem, that you
should know the righteousness of God. So אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi
Eleazar, so what does that mean, the righteousness of God? So you
know, the פשט Pshat is of course that God changed the ברכה
Bracha to a, the קללה Kelalah to a ברכה, Bracha, but let's
see, אמר להם הקדוש ברוך הוא לישראל, Amar Lahem Ha-kadosh Baruch Hu
Le-yisrael, God says to ישראל, דעו כמה צדקות עשיתי עמכם, De'u Kamah
Tzidkot Asiti Imachem, know how many acts of kindness or righteousness, kindness
I did to you,
שלא כעסתי בימי בלעם הרשע, She-lo Ka'asti Bi-ymei Bil'am Ha-rasha, I never
allowed myself to get angry even for the infinitesimal second during that
period of בלעם, Bil'am, שאלמלי כעסתי, She-ilmalei Ka'asti, had I given myself
that one moment of anger, לא נשתייר משונאיהם של ישראל שריד ופליט,
Lo Nishtayer Mi-sone'eihem Shel Yisrael Sarid U-falit, then none of the enemies,
meaning the Jews, meaning the Jews, not even the tiniest remnant would
have been around because he would have tapped into that anger.
And how should I get angry that the God has not been
angry towards? So we normally read it as angry towards, but here
it means God has not been angry at all. He's prevented himself
from getting angry. מלמד שכל אותם הימים לא זעם. Melamed she'kol otam
ha'yamim lo za'am. You see all of those days God did not
get angry in order to protect us from this. וכמה זעמו Ve'khama
za'amo and now repeating what we said, how much is זעם? za'am?
רגע. rega. וכמה רגע, Ve'khama rega, how much is a רגע? rega?
So אמר רב אבין ואיתימא רב אבינא, Amar Rav Avin ve'itima Rav
Avina, רגע כמימריה. rega k'meimrei. Now like we said before, one in
fifty-eight thousandth or whatever, but here we're saying רגע כמימריה, rega k'meimrei,
the amount of time it takes to say it, רגע. rega. So
it's still like a half of a second, but it's still not
as tiny as before. Now a little bit of a sidebar, תוספות,
Tosafot,
if you took a look at תוספות, Tosafot, שאילמלי כעסתי לא נשתייר,
She'ilmalei ka'asti lo nishtayer, תוספות Tosafot ואם תאמר מה יכול לומר באותה
שעת רגע. Ve'im tomar ma yakhol lomar be'otah sha'at rega. So okay
he could have tapped in if he found that moment, but what
could he say in that half of a second? How are you
going to say something to tap into it? Like what can how
can you pray to curse them you know in a half of
a second? So he says יש לומר "כלם". Yesh lomar "kalem". He
could have said the word כלם, kalem, destroy them. So he could
have got something in that half second. אי נמי Ee nami says
תוספות Tosafot מאחר שהיה מתחיל קללתו באותה שעה, me'acher she'haya matchil kilalato
be'otah sha'ah, if he would have started with that second, then היה
מזיק אפילו לאחר מכאן, haya mazik afilu le'achar mikan, then anything he
would have said after would have still tapped into that anger. So
that's interesting in two ways. Number one is you know just in
terms of thinking about it in human terms, if you can tap
in, you know, sort of tap into somebody when they're angry and
exploit their anger then it'll you know spill beyond its normal bounds
and you can get it to extend outward. And from an interesting
halakhic point,
the רוגאטשובר Rogatchover was was asked once like whatever there's a question,
what if you're making סוף זמן תפילה, sof zman tfila, right, it's
like a second before שקיעה shkiyah or something like that, a second
before you know the end of the time of דאווענינג, davening, can
you דאווען daven if you can't get the whole דאווענינג davening in
during the time? Do you have to start at סוף זמן תפילה,
sof zman tfila, do you have to end by סוף זמן תפילה?
sof zman tfila? So he said based on this תוספות Tosafot you
see it's enough to start even if you don't end by that
time. As long as you start at the right time that's enough.
So anyway, but that is תוספות Tosafot but that I think the
first point is more relevant to the story about what it means
to sort of tap into somebody else's anger. I also think that
there's an important point about the idea that God does get angry
but only for a tiny period of time. You know
again translating it in human terms, you know sometimes we do need
a moment to sort of vent our anger at things. But the
idea is if you can contain it into a small safe period
of time you know and don't have it spill over, you know
that's sort of the proper way of handling things. So okay you
have a moment of anger, but it's only a tiny moment and
that's what you use to sort of vent and not that that's
your sort of dominant feature. I also wrote something up on the
blog if you saw about also you know that there's an idea
in general about והלכת בדרכיו ve'halachta bi'drachav and emulating God. And you
know what does that mean? Like some people think that by emulating
God it means that we have to sort of you know be
judgmental about everybody else you know because God also punishes and is
angry and I you know and sort of calls things evil you
know bad and so on. But I think this גמרא Gemara is
very important that the okay that's an aspect you know to sort
of look at the bad and call it out and so on
and be angry about it. But that's a רגע, rega, you know
that's a sixty thousandth of a second that is not the dominant
aspect of what it means to sort of of what God's identity
is and what it means for us I would say to emulate
that. Okay so that is the story about בלעם. Bilaam. Now we
continue.
ומנלן U'minalan oh I didn't finish we didn't finish one wrap up.
ומנלן דרגע רתח U'minalan de'rega ratach and how do we know that
God does get angry for that for that רגע? rega? I mean
we quoted a פסוק pasuk before but that was about זעם, zaam,
here it's רתח, ratach, maybe it's slightly different. But anyway שנאמר כי
רגע באפו חיים ברצונו. shene'emar ki rega be'apo chayim bi'retzono. The anger
is a רגע, rega, but lifetime is in God's good graces, in
God's will. So that's only a tiny infinitesimal part. ואיבעית אימא מהכא
Ve'iba'it eima me'hacha or or perhaps from here, חבי כמעט רגע, chavi
kim'at rega, wait for a רגע rega עד יעבור זעם ad ya'avor
za'am until the anger passes over. Okay so again it's only for
a רגע. rega. ואימת רתח Ve'eimat ratach and when exactly is that
moment that God gets angry now that we're talking about it? And
אמר אביי בהנך תלת שעי קמייתא amar Abaye be'hanach tlat sha'ei kamayta
in the first three hours of the day, sometimes between six and
nine a.m. כי חיורתא כרבלתא דתרנגולא ki chivarta karbalta de'tarnagola when the
when the crest of what's it called the crest of a rooster?
Crown? Crest? What's that called? Yeah. One of them. Anyway of which
one?
Okay what?
Comb?
Oh the comb, thank you. The comb of a rooster turns white.
וכי סומקי Ve'ki sumki I'm sorry. I'm sorry, where was I? כי
חיוורתא קבלתא דתרנגולא ki chivarta kablata d'tarnegola וקאי אחד כרעא v'kai achad
kar'a and the rooster stands on one leg, on one leg. That's
when the moment that God is angry. So the Gemara says: כל
שעתא ושעתא נמי קאי הכי? kol sha'ata v'sha'ata nami kai hachi? What
do you mean, it's always like this? So the Gemara says: no,
כל שעתא אית ביה שורקי סומקי. kol sha'ata is bei shurki sumki.
Normally there are some red streaks in the comb. בההיא שעתא, bahai
sha'ata, where are we? לית ביה שורקי סומקי. leit bei shurki sumki.
At that moment there are no red streaks, it's all white. Now
we have a story about this. ההוא צדוקי דהוה בשיבבותיה דרבי יהושע
בן לוי. hahu tzadoki d'hava b'shivvutei d'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. There was
a certain Sadducee in the neighborhood of Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi. הוה
קא מצער ליה טובא בקראי. hava ka m'tza'er lei tuva bikra'ei. He
was sort of giving him a lot of affliction, meaning with פסוקים,
pesukim, meaning he was say, "What about this pasuk? What about this
pasuk?" meaning he was constantly sort of challenging him about the rabbinic
tradition and bothering him about פסוקים. pesukim. So it wasn't just that
he was personally annoying him, it was also somewhat of a religious
threat that he was constantly raising these issues and making trouble. So
what did he do?
יומא חד, yoma chad, so one day Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi שקיל
תרנגולא ואוקמיה בין כרעא דערסא. shakal tarnegola v'okmei bein kar'a d'arsa. He
took a rooster and he put it by the legs of the
bed ועיין ביה v'ayein bei and he was watching it, waiting to
find that split second when it would turn fully white, the comb,
and that he could use that to tap into God's anger and
to curse this צדוקי, tzadoki, like he was doing like we said
Bilaam tried to do. וסבר כי מטא ההיא זימנא, v'savar ki mata
hahu zimna, he figured when that moment comes, אלטייה, alatiyei, I'll curse
him. כי מטא ההיא שעתא, ki mata hahu sha'ata, when that moment
came, ניים, niyeim, he fell asleep. אמר, he said: שמע מינה לאו
אורחא למיעבד הכי. shma mina lav orcha l'me'evad hachi. I see it
is not the right way of doing things to act like this,
to try to tap into that moment of anger. ורחמיו על כל
מעשיו כתיב. v'rachamav al kol ma'asav ktiv. God's compassion is on all
of God's creatures. וכתיב גם
ענוש לצדיק לא טוב. v'chtiv gam anos l'tzaddik lo tov. Even for,
you know, to bring about somebody's punishment is not the right way
for a צדיק tzaddik to act. So even when you're doing it
לשם שמים, l'shem shamayim, you know, you should... this is not the
way people who are doing things לשם שמים l'shem shamayim should be
doing, to try to be tapping into God's anger to try to
bring punishment upon people. תני משמיה דרבי מאיר, tani mishmei d'Rabbi Meir,
we learned in the name of Rabbi Meir: בשעה שהחמה זורחת וכל
מלכי מזרח ומערב מניחים כתריהם בראשיהם ומשתחוים לחמה. b'sha'ah shehachamah zorachat v'chol
malchei mizrach u'maarav manichim kitreihem b'rasheihem u'mishtachavim lachamah. Now if you want
to know when God gets angry, it's not just arbitrary. Here's when
God gets angry: at the moment that the sun rises and all
of the kings of the East and the West, you know, put
off their crowns and they bow down to the sun to show
that the sun is the true god, at that moment מיד כועס
הקדוש ברוך הוא. miyad ko'es hakadosh baruch hu.
That's when God gets angry. So it's not just arbitrary, it's in
reaction to the fact that, you know,
basically almost everybody in the world abandons God and that's fully expressed
at this moment. So according to him, I guess it's easier to
know that moment. Anyway, so now the Gemara continues. Now we are
done with the issue of what do you call it, of the
anger and of Bilaam. ואמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי. v'amar Rabbi
Yochanan mishum Rabbi Yossi. Now we're still with statements of Rabbi Yochanan
in the name of Rabbi Yossi. We had... that was the previous
statement, this is this statement:
טובה מרדות אחת בלבו של אדם. tova mardut achat b'libo shel adam.
This is a very sort of insightful, it's all insightful, but anyway
something that really resonates. Statement here: better is one moment of sort
of
internalizing, you know, sort of a self-internalizing
of a message. That's what the word מרדות mardut here means, the
way Rashi says to be מרדה marda means to beat down, but
it means you're beating your own heart down. You're sort of taking
to heart a message in a person's heart. יותר מכמה מלקיות, yoter
mikama malkiyot, better than many sort of being beaten from the outside.
שנאמר ורדפה אחרי מאהביה. shenemar v'radfa acharei me'ahaveha. This is a, you
know, the נביא's משל navi's mashal about how when Israel leaves God,
it's like a woman who abandons her husband and commits adultery and
runs after all of her lovers, and you know, and then it
speaks about that she's being beaten up and that she, you know,
basically describes her in a very fallen state, and not just morally
fallen, but you know, bad things happening to her. And then at
the end it says ואמרה אלכה ואשובה אל אישי הראשון כי טוב
לי אז מעתה. v'amra elcha v'ashuva el ishi harishon ki tov li
az me'ata. The turning point is when she realizes it herself. She
says, "I should return to my first husband." So as we know,
you know, people can... a million things can, you know, you can
try to tell something to somebody a million times, people can be
in therapy, but until somebody finally like begins to hear the message
themselves and brings it inward and internalizes it, you know, a million
other... there's so much that happens in your life that could be
telling you you're acting in the wrong way and that you've got
to change course, but it doesn't... it's not going to make a
difference until you finally have learned to internalize that message. So I
think a very
on-target, a really resonant point here. So now the Gemara continues. וריש
לקיש אמר יותר ממאה מלקיות. v'Resh Lakish amar yoter mime'ah malkiyot. It's
even more powerful than even being beaten a hundred times, you know,
that should give you. evidence that you're not doing the right thing,
it's not going to make a difference until you bring it inward.
שנאמר, Shene'emar, it says תחת גערה במבין מהכות כסיל מאה. tachas ga'arah
b'mevin m'hakos ksil me'ah. Better is a גערה ga'arah yelling to an
understanding person, meaning if that sort of מוסר mussar is brought inside
is better than beating a foolish person a hundred times. Okay. ואמר
רב יוחנן משום רבי יוסי. ve'amar rav yochanan mishum rabi yosi. Another
statement of רב יוחנן rav yochanan in the name of רבי יוסי,
rabi yosi, but this statement ties back to earlier themes about יסורין
של אהבה. yissurin shel ahavah. Let's take a look. שלשה דברים ביקש
משה מלפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. sheloshah devarim bikkesh moshe milifnei hakadosh baruch
hu. Moshe asked three things from God, ונתן לו, venasan lo, and
they were given to him. ביקש שתשרה שכינה על ישראל,
bikkesh shetishreh
shechinah al yisrael, that the divine presence should rest on Israel, ונתן
לו, venasan lo, God granted it, שנאמר, Shene'emar, הלא בלכתך עמנו. halo
belechtecha immanu. Now this is of course what Moshe asked for, but
he asked for, you know, you got to go with us. This
is after the חטא העגל cheit ha'eigel where God says basically I'm
that's it, I'm getting out of here, I'll send my angel. And
Moshe said no, we want you to go with us. And then
in the end of it, God says, you know, God says, okay,
גם את הדבר אשר דברת אעשה. gam es hadavar asher dibbarta e'eseh.
I will do what you have asked for. So we're proving that
God answered by showing that Moshe asked, for in the end God
says I'll do it. So number one, God you should go with
us. And number two,
ביקש ושלא תשרה שכינה על עובדי כוכבים. bikkesh veshelo tishreh shechinah al
ovdei chochavim. This should be unique between God and Israel, that the
שכינה shechinah should not rest upon the non-Jews. Doesn't mean that there
shouldn't be a relationship with the non-Jews, but the unique relationship of
God's שכינה shechinah dwelling among us should be a unique relationship we
have with God. שנאמר, as it says, ונתן לו, venasan lo, שנאמר,
ונפלינו
אני ועמך. veniflinu ani ve'ammcha. We will be distinct that we will
have this unique relationship with you God. And as the גמרא Gemara
said earlier and you know about the whole thing about God wearing
תפילין tefillin and the theme of דברים devarim that the whole ספר
דברים sefer devarim that we're reading, that is an ongoing theme of
דברים, devarim, but the unique relationship of Israel with God forged through
the Exodus and and you know these events. And the following one
is ביקש להודיעו דרכיו של הקדוש ברוך הוא. bikkesh lehodio derachav shel
hakadosh baruch hu. He wanted to know God's ways, how God acts
in terms of justice in this world. ונתן לו, venasan lo, that
was given to him, שנאמר, הודיעני נא את דרכך. hodieni na es
derachecha. Let me understand your ways. אמר לפניו, amar lefanav, he said
to Him, רבונו של עולם, ribbono shel olam, Master of the Universe,
מפני מה יש צדיק וטוב לו ויש צדיק ורע לו יש רשע
וטוב לו ויש רשע ורע לו. mippenei mah yesh tzaddik vetov lo
veyesh tzaddik vera lo yesh rasha vetov lo veyesh rasha vera lo.
The world seems random. Righteous people have it good, but some righteous
people have it bad. Wicked people have it good, have it bad,
but some wicked people have it good. It doesn't work the way
it seems like in the תורה Torah it's supposed to work, which
is the righteous are rewarded and the wicked are punished. Now, of
course, this is obviously a question that bothered חז"ל, chazal, as we
saw before about יסורין של אהבה. yissurin shel ahavah. And here they
are understanding that משה moshe is the one posing this question to
God. How does that fit in the theme of what's happening in
the פרשה, parashah, right? I mean משה moshe does say הודיעני דרכך,
hodieni derachecha, so it's a good thing to read into the הודיעני
דרכך. hodieni derachecha. But you know the הודיעני דרכך hodieni derachecha of
the פסוקים pesukim is basically God says אל רחום וחנון el rachum
vechanun and so on, which is basically understood as a way that
משה moshe says that I can, you know, sort of
appeal to this when you get angry like you're angry now, that
you're an אל רחום וחנון. el rachum vechanun. Here the גמרא Gemara
makes it a much sort of broader question about justice in general
in the world, and in a way that also makes sense. Like
you know משה moshe is saying, look God, you want to punish
them, you don't want to go with us, whatever, the world, you
know, it's not always consistent. It doesn't seem like the righteous are
always getting punished and so on. So explain to me what's going
on here and how it works. So let's take a look. So
what's the answer? So the answer is the following. אמר לו, amar
lo, He said to him, משה, moshe, משה, moshe, let me tell
you. צדיק וטוב לו צדיק בן צדיק. צדיק ורע לו צדיק בן
רשע. tzaddik vetov lo tzaddik ben tzaddik tzaddik vera lo tzaddik ben
rasha. A
צדיק tzaddik that has it good is a צדיק tzaddik the child
of a צדיק. tzaddik. A צדיק tzaddik that has it bad is
a צדיק tzaddik the child of a רשע. rasha. רשע וטוב לו
רשע בן צדיק. rasha vetov lo rasha ben tzaddik. A רשע rasha
who has it good is a רשע rasha the child of a
צדיק. tzaddik. רשע ורע לו רשע בן רשע. rasha vera lo rasha
ben rasha. A רשע rasha who has it bad is the son
of a רשע. rasha. Which basically means what? Which basically means that
people are punished for the sins
of their parents, so if it's inconsistent with your deeds, it's because
we're still clearing the ledger regarding your parents' deeds. Okay. Now that's
maybe an answer, but A, does that always work? But besides that
is that if you know that's an approach that even in the
תורה Torah. is challenged about whether people suffer for their parents' sins.
So let's see where the גמרא Gemara, continues. אמר מר, amar mar,
so צדיק
וטוב לו, tzaddik vetov lo, so that's the statement, but now we're
going to reflect on it. צדיק וטוב לו צדיק בן צדיק tzaddik
vetov lo tzaddik ben tzaddik. צדיק ורע לו צדיק בן רשע. tzaddik
vera lo tzaddik ben rasha. איני? eini? Is that really true? והכתיב
פוקד עון אבות על בנים. vehachtiv poked avon avos al banim. On
the one hand, you have a פסוק pasuk that says God visits
the sins of the fathers on the children. וכתיב ובנים לא יומתו
על אבות, vechativ uvanim lo yumtu al avos, and another verse says
that they don't die for the sins of their fathers. ורמינהי, uraminihi,
he cried out, we say why do these פסוקים pesukim contradict? We
weren't the only ones who said that. ירמיהו yirmeyahu said the פסוקים
pesukim contradict. ומשנינן, umeshaninan, and the answer we give is, לא קשיא,
lo kashya, it's not a question. הא כשאוחזים מעשה. ha keshe'ochazim ma'aseh.
When do you suffer for your parents' deeds? When you continue in
your parents' ways, but if you actually break from your parents' ways
you don't suffer for their deeds.
Now of course it's interesting, even that answer I'm not sure sort
of fits in with the way we think about things. You might
think that if somebody grew up with bad parents and in a
bad environment, to some degree they should be a little bit
explained, sort of cuts down on their culpability because they had fewer
opportunities and they were brought up in a bad environment, so their
personal responsibility might be less. But of course the גמרא Gemara working
with this theology in the תורה Torah? says there is a time
when when it's seen like you're a bad seed and this is
a bad family and you're a continuation of your father, that you
are somehow punished, or the parents, that you are punished for the
sins of your parents. But so yes, it doesn't always work about
degree of personal fault. But anyway, that's the time it works that
way and not the way the גמרא Gemara said the first answer
which said it always works that way, that there's always a ledger
to clear. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא הכי קאמר ליה, ella
hachi ka'amar lei,
so how are we going to still explain this issue that sometimes
things seem unjust? So okay, let's try another answer. צדיק וטוב לו
צדיק גמור צדיק ורע לו צדיק שאינו גמור רשע וטוב לו רשע
שאינו גמור רשע ורע לו רשע גמור. tzaddik v'tov lo, tzaddik gamur,
tzaddik v'ra lo, tzaddik she'eino gamur, rasha v'tov lo, rasha she'eino gamur,
rasha v'ra lo, rasha gamur. So now we are moving away from
the whole idea of sins of the parents and we're saying yeah,
it's all about your deeds, but sometimes nobody is
perfect, so if you're not a perfect צדיק, tzaddik, not a perfect
רשע, rasha, people are mixed. So sometimes you could be overwhelmed basically
a צדיק, tzaddik, but there's going to be some suffering in order
to clear the ledger for the small bad deeds, or the reverse,
basically a רשע, rasha, there'll be some reward to clear the ledger
for the small good deeds. Of course all of this assumes that
the basic reward is in עולם הבא, Olam Haba, right? Because if
the,
well no, not necessarily, I take that back.
Well it still does because it depends how bad is the bad
that a person is suffering. If somebody's a צדיק tzaddik and they
mostly have it good and they have a few moments of suffering,
a few experiences of suffering, then that exactly corresponds to their ledger
of deeds. But if you have a צדיק tzaddik that has it
miserable his whole life or a רשע rasha that has it good
his whole life, then the only way to explain that is we're
not just clearing the ledger but that the balance of it is
going to get paid up in עולם הבא. Olam Haba. So part
of this answer does also assume the idea that the balance of
it will get paid up in עולם הבא. Olam Haba. Okay, so
now the גמרא, and this obviously is an interesting counterpoint point to
the discussion we had before about יסורין של אהבה. yissurin shel ahavah.
And now the
גמרא continues, ופליגא דרבי מאיר, u'pliga d'Rabbi Meir, and this argues on
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. דאמר רבי מאיר, d'amar Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says שתים נתנו לו ואחת לא נתנו לו, shtayim nitnu
lo v'achas lo nitna lo, two of them were God gave but
the third God did not give, שנאמר, וחנתי את אשר אחן, v'chanoti
et asher achon, God says back to משה, Moshe, I will be
kind to the people I'll be kind with, אף על פי שאינו
הגון, af al pi she'eino hagun, even though it's not deserved, ורחמתי
את אשר ארחם, v'richamti et asher arachem, I'll be compassionate to whoever
I choose to be compassionate, אף על פי שאינו הגון, af al
pi she'eino hagun, even though he's not deserving. So basically says משה,
Moshe, you ain't going to figure it out, I'll do what I'll
do, there's no way you're going to figure it out. Now on
the one hand that sounds like, okay, but that really only answers
part of it, that answers the רשע וטוב לו, rasha v'tov lo,
that God sometimes is just
kind, gives undeserved kindness, which is very nice to think that, very
nice that that's one aspect of it. But the question is what
about the other part, the צדיק ורע לו? tzaddik v'ra lo? It
doesn't say sometimes I'll just be mean even though he doesn't deserve
it. So anyway, but part of this answer, even though it only
answers half, is important and this gets to the fact that the
depth of the point here I would say is not the answer
but it's the question. It's the fact that חז"ל Chazal are basically
grappling with the fact that the world doesn't work in the reward
and punishment way that we are led to believe by reading the
תורה. How did we make sense of that? So with that יסורין,
yissurin, now having משה Moshe ask how we make sense of that?
So we could try to give an answer, yeah, it'll all work
out in עולם הבא, Olam Haba, there's a ledger to clear, it'll
all work out. But you know what, sometimes that doesn't even satisfy.
And רבי מאיר'ס Rabbi Meir's answer is you know what, we're not
going to know the answer. We're not going to be able to
understand how what God does is just and how things are properly
rewarded or not based on what we see in this world. And
that's also an answer sometimes חז"ל Chazal give, like when the חז"ל
Chazal say that the heavenly angels saw רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's flesh
being flayed from him and said זו תורה וזו שכרה? zu Torah
v'zu s'charah? Is this the reward for תורה? God basically said silence,
this is my גזירה מלפני. gezeirah milfanai. So the גזירה מלפני gezeirah
milfanai is like a counterpart to וחנתי את אשר אחן. v'chanoti et
asher achon. Sometimes you're not going to understand. But so it's really
חז"ל Chazal grappling with it and at the same time recognizing that
we won't always have the answer to that question. It's also of
course the question of איוב, Iyov, where the... issue about צדיק ורע
לו Tzaddik V'Ra Lo there was no good answer to that. Okay,
so now the גמרא continues the following, where are we? Okay, ויאמר
לא תוכל לראות פני, V'yomar Lo Tuchal Lirot Panai, you cannot see
my
face. תנא משמיה דרבי יהושע בן קרחה, Tana Mishmei D'Rabbi Yehoshua Ben
Korcha, כך אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה. Kach Amar Hakadosh Baruch Hu
L'Moshe. This is what God said to Moshe. I love this line.
כשרציתי, Kesheratziti, when I wanted to reveal myself to you at the
סנה, Sneh, לא רצית, Lo Ratzita, you weren't interested. עכשיו שאתה רוצה,
Achshav She'atah Rotze, now you're interested, איני רוצה, Eini Rotze, I'm no
longer interested. So again, something I think we can relate to at
different times of our lives. So it's very nice now you want
to see my face. You blew your chance. Okay, when I wanted,
you weren't interested. ופליגא דרבי
שמואל בר נחמני, Upliga D'Rabbi Shmuel Bar Nachmani, this argues on Rabbi
Shmuel Bar Nachmani. אמר רבי יונתן דאמר רבי שמואל בר נחmני אמר
רבי יונתן, Amar Rabbi Yonatan De'amar Rabbi Shmuel Bar Nachmani Amar Rabbi
Yonatan,
בשכר שלש זכה לשלש. Bischar Shalosh Zachah L'shalosh. For the merit of
three things, Moshe merited three things. בשכר ויסתר משה פניו, Bischar Vayaster
Moshe Panav, Moshe hid his face, זכה לקלסתר פנים, Zachah L'klaster Panim,
he merited that when he,
after he emerged from the אהל מועד, Ohel Moed, his face shone.
So because he hid his face, it was not yet appropriate then
for him to have that intimate connection to God. Later when it
was appropriate, he had the shining of the face. בשכר כי ירא,
Bischar Ki Yarei, because he was afraid to draw close, זכה וייראו
מגשת אליו, Zachah Vayiru Migeshet Elav, בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael was afraid
to draw close to him. He had achieved that status, but he
knew initially that he wasn't ready for it, then he had achieved
it and then he merited that in relationship to בני ישראל. Bnei
Yisrael. ובשכר מהביט, Uvischar Mehabit, and because of the fact that he
was afraid to stare at God, זכה ולתמונת השם יביט, Zachah Uletmunat
Hashem Yabit, that he was able to stare at or to gaze
at the vision of God. So it's actually a very beautiful parallel
showing exactly those words occur later and parallel in the exact same
way of his intimate connection with God that occurred later on that
he did not have at that time. And the way this is
different is this says it's good that he didn't look at that
time, and the other way says God was like upset, you didn't
want to do it when I wanted to. But here it's saying
actually it was a good thing that actually Moshe realized he was
not yet ready for that experience. And that actually, interesting, רמב"ם Rambam
uses that in מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevuchim in the intellectual plane. רמב"ם
Rambam says, certain intellectual endeavors, particularly philosophy and theology, you should not
do until you're ready. And Moshe understood that and he was not
yet ready to have a vision of God and to see God
directly and therefore he was correct to hide his face. So it's
an interesting question about like whether God had wanted the greater intimacy
then or whether Moshe actually it was not appropriate. There are times
when intimacy was ready and that was not yet the time. Let's
just finish to the end of the page. I have no idea
what we're going to do about being so far behind. והסירותי את
כפי, Vahasiroti Et Kapi, I will remove my hand, וראית את אחרי,
Vraita Et Achora, you'll see my backside. אמר רב הונא בר ביזנא
אמר רבי שמעון חסידא, Amar Rav Huna Bar Bizna Amar Rabbi Shimon
Chasida, מלמד שהראה הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה קשר של תפילין. Melamed She'herah
Hakadosh Baruch Hu L'Moshe Kesher Shel Tefillin. Okay, so that's to tie
it back to, all right, forget the pun, tie it back to
the discussion of תפילין. Tefillin. So when you see God's back, what
do you see? So the back is you see the תפילין. Tefillin.
So again, that's also on the one hand it's removing it from
the anthropomorphism, you're not seeing a physical person, you're seeing a תפילין,
Tefillin, and you're also seeing, you know, sort of the connecting back
to that sort of holy thing that we can relate to, the
תפילין. Tefillin. I'm not exactly sure what more to do with the
fact that it's pointing out קשר של תפילין Kesher Shel Tefillin except
the desire to move away from the like seeing God's head per
se. ואמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי יוסי, V'amar Rabbi Yochanan Mishum Rabbi
Yosi, כל דבור ודבור שיצא מפי הקדוש ברוך הוא לטובה אפילו על
תנאי לא חזר בו. Kol Dibur V'dibur Sheyatza Mipi Hakadosh Baruch Hu
Letovah Afilu Al Tnai Lo Chazar Bo. Anything that God says he'll
do for good, even if it's on a condition, God won't take
it back. Which again is a little bit in contrast to the
גמרא earlier that people were afraid that שמא יגרום החטא, Shema Yigrom
Hachet, that they might sin and lose what God had promised. Here
it says anything God promises he won't take back.
מנלן? Minalan? ממשה רבנו. MiMoshe Rabbeinu. שנאמר, for Moshe, God says, הרף
ממני ואשמידם ואעשה אותך לגוי עצום. Heref Mimeni V'ashmidem V'e'eseh Otcha L'goy
Atzum. Leave me alone, I'll wipe them out and you'll be a
great nation. אף על גב דבעא משה רחמי עלה דמילתא ובטלה, Af
Al Gav Deba'a Moshe Rachamei Alei D'milta Uvatla, Moshe prayed about it
and annulled the decree. אפילו הכי אוקמה בזרעיה. Afilu Hachi Ukmah Bezar'ei.
This idea of ואעשה אותך לגוי עצום Ve'eseh Otcha L'goy Atzum which
was connected to destroying בני ישראל. Bnei Yisrael. So if you don't
destroy בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, you're not, I'm not going to make
you a גוי עצום. Goy Atzum. Nevertheless, Moshe became a גוי עצום.
Goy Atzum. How did that happen? His children, שנאמר, בני משה גרשום
ואליעזר. Bnei Moshe Gershom V'eliezer. ויהיו בני, V'yihyu Bnei, this is in
דברי הימים, Divrei Hayamim, ויהיו בני אליעזר רחביה הראש ובני רחביה רבו
למעלה למעלה. V'yihyu Bnei Eliezer Rechavyah Harosh Uvnei Rechavyah Rabu L'malah L'malah.
And the sons of Rechavyah became very, very great, were increased
greatly, greatly. ותני רב יוסף, Vetani Rav Yosef, למעלה מששים רבוא, L'malah
Mishishim Ribo, greater than the 600,000 that came out of Egypt. אתיא
רביה רביה, Atya Ravya Ravya, כתיב הכא רבו למעלה, Ketiv Hacha Rabu
L'malah, here it says they increased greatly, exceedingly. וכתיב התם, Uchtiv Hatam,
בני ישראל פרו וישרצו וירבו. Bnei Yisrael Paru Vayishretzu Vayirbu. So you
see that he became as Moshe's children became as large as בני
ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, so ואעשה אותך לגוי גדול Ve'eseh Otcha L'goy Gadol
was fulfilled. So we will end here. Just to say since I've
been quoting רמב"ם, Rambam, רמב"ם Rambam has a nice explanation of what
it means to be the back of God, not seeing the face,
means we can never really understand God, but we can understand God
through history and through God's actions and through how we see how
God operates in the world. So you don't see the essence of
God, but if you would, you see as it were the wake
of God, you see, you see the back of God, you see
the you see everything that God has done and through that we
can gain an appreciation of what God is. So we'll end with
that now, but again, I have no idea how we're going to
deal with the fact that we are now a דף and a
half behind, maybe we can try to figure it out over email.
Have you been able to hear me okay?